<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A solemne and seasonable warning to the noblemen, barons, gentlemen, burrows, ministers, and commons of Scotland: as also to the Scotish armies without and within that kingdom. From the Generall Assembly, 12 Feb. 1645. And the humble remonstrance of the aforesaid Assembly to the King, 13. Feb. 1645.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79762</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4259H</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E293_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113099</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113099)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E293[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A solemne and seasonable warning to the noblemen, barons, gentlemen, burrows, ministers, and commons of Scotland: as also to the Scotish armies without and within that kingdom. From the Generall Assembly, 12 Feb. 1645. And the humble remonstrance of the aforesaid Assembly to the King, 13. Feb. 1645.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Remonstrance of the Generall Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland to His Majestie. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Raworth, in the yeer 1645. According to the copy printed at Edinburgh.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes: The remonstrance of the Generall Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland to His Majestie (Wing C4255).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113099:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SOLEMNE AND SEASONABLE WARNING To the Noblemen, Barons, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Burrows, Miniſters, and Commons of <hi>Scotland:</hi> As alſo to the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Armies without and within that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Generall Aſſembly,</hi> 12 Feb. 1645.</p>
            <p>And the humble Remonſtrance of the aforeſaid Aſſembly to the King, 13. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall the Watch-men of Sion be ſilent, when Iſrael is in trouble?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. Raworth,</hi> in the yeer 1645. <hi>According to the Copy printed at</hi> Edinburgh.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113099:2"/>
            <head>12 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1645. <hi>Poſtmeridiem.</hi> Seſſ. XVIII.</head>
            <p>THe Generall Aſſembly, after mature delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, having found it moſt neceſſary that this whole Nation be timely Warned, and duly Informed of their preſent Dangers, and the Remedies to be uſed, and Duties to be done for preventing and removing thereof; Doth ordain this Warning to be fortwith Printed and Publiſhed, and ſent to all the Preſbyteries in this Kingdom, as alſo to the Preſbyteries that are with our Armies. And that each Preſbytery, immediately after the receipt hereof, take ſpeedy courſe for the Reading of it in every Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion within their bounds, upon the Lords day after the forenoons Sermon, and before the Bleſſing: And that they give account of their diligence herein to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly; Who have hereby Power and Warrant to try and cenſure ſuch as ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne or ſlight the ſaid Warning, or ſhall refuſe or neglect to obey this Ordinance.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113099:2"/>
            <head>A Solemne and Seaſonable Warning to the Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Burrows, Miniſters, and Commons of <hi>Scotland:</hi> As alſo to our Armies without and within this Kingdom. From the Generall Aſſembly, <hi>12 Feb. 1645.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Cauſe of God in this Kingdom, both in the beginnings and progreſſe of it, hath been carried, through much craft and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty oppoſition of Enemies, and through other perplexities and dangers; God ſo diſpoſing, for the greater glory of his manifold and marvellous Wiſdom, and his invincible Power, &amp; for our greater tryall.</p>
            <p>Theſe dangers both from without and from within, together with the remedies thereof, have been from time to time repreſented and held forth, in the many publick Supplications of this Kirk and Kingdom to the King, and in their many Declarations, Remonſtrances, Letters, Acts, and other publick Intimations: Particularly by a neceſſary Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, publiſhed by the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly in <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1643. And by the Remonſtrance of the ſame Commiſſioners to the Convention of Eſtates in <hi>July</hi> thereafter, concerning the Dangers of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Remedies of theſe Dangers. Which Warning and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance at that time had, by the bleſſing of God, very good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable effects. And now the Generall Aſſembly it ſelf, being by a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Providence, and upon extraordinary occaſions called together, while God is writing bitter things againſt this Land in great Letters, which he that runs may read: and knowing that we cannot be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God, nor our own conſciences, nor the expectation of others, if from this chief Watch-Tower we ſhould give no Seaſonable Warning to the City of God: While we think of theſe things; <hi>For Sions ſake we will not hold our peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake we will not reſt:</hi> truſting that God will give, though not to all, yet to many, a ſeeing Eye, a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ear, and an underſtanding Heart: For <hi>who is wiſe and he ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe things, prudent and he ſhall know them; For the Wayes of the Lord are right, and the juſt ſhall walk in them; but the tranſgreſſors ſhall fall therein, and the wicked ſhall do wickedly, and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which we principally intend, is to hold forth (ſo far as the Lord gives us light) how this Nation ought to be affected with their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113099:3"/>preſent Mercies and Judgements; What uſe is to be made of the Lords dealings: And, what is required of a people ſo dealt with.</p>
            <p>Had we been timely awaked, and taken warning, either from the exemplary judgements of other Nations; or from Gods threatnings by the mouths of his ſervants amongſt our ſelves; or from our own former viſitations, and namely, The Sword, threatned and drawn againſt us, both at home and from abroad, but at that time through the forbearance of God, put up in the Sheath again, we might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the miſeries under which now we groane. But the Cup of trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, before taken out of our hands, is again come about to us, that we may drink deeper of it: And although when theſe bloody Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Iriſh Rebels, together with ſome degenerate, unnaturall, and perfidious Countrey-men of our own, did firſt lift up their heads, and enter this Kingdom in a hoſtile way, it was looked upon as a light matter, and the great judgement which hath ſince appeared in it, not apprehended: yet now we are made more ſenſible, that they are <hi>The rod of Gods wrath, and the ſtaffe in their hand,</hi> which hath ſtricken us theſe three times, is <hi>his indignation. He hath ſhewed his people hard things, and made us to drink the wine of aſtoniſhment.</hi> Take we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore notice of the hand that ſmiteth us, <hi>for affliction cometh not forth of the duſt, neither doth trouble ſpring out of the ground. There is no evill in the City</hi> nor Countrey <hi>which the Lord hath not done.</hi> He it is <hi>that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the light, and createth darkneſſe; Who maketh peace, and createth evill:</hi> He it is that hath given a charge to the Sword, <hi>ſo that it cannot be ſtill:</hi> He it is that hath his other <hi>Arrows ready upon the ſtring to ſhoot at us,</hi> the Peſtilence and Famine.</p>
            <p>In the next place, let us apply our hearts to know, and to ſearch, and to ſeek out wiſdom, and the reaſon of things, and to underſtand the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of this preſent judgement, and Gods meaning in it: For though <hi>the Almighty giveth not an accompt of any of his matters, and hath his way in the Sea, and his path in the deep waters which cannot be traced;</hi> Yet he is pleaſed by the light of his Word and Spirit; by the voice of our own conſciences, and by that which is written and ingraven upon our judgement, as with the point of a Diamond and a Pen of iron, to make known in ſome meaſure his meaning unto his ſervants. <hi>God hath ſpoken once, yea twice, yet man perceiveth not;</hi> Therefore now hath he made this rod to ſpeak aloud the third time, that we may <hi>hear the voice of the rod, and who hath appointed it.</hi> That which the rod pointeth at, is not any guilt of Rebellion or diſloyalty in us, as the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> do ſlander and belye the Solemne League and Covenant of the three Kingdoms, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113099:3"/>we are ſo far from repenting of, that we cannot remember or mention it without great joy and thankfulneſſe to God, as that which hath drawn many bleſſings after it, and unto which God hath given mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and evident teſtimonies; for no ſooner was the Covenant begun to be taken in <hi>England,</hi> but ſenſibly the condition of affairs there was changed to the better; and though a little before, the Enemy was coming in like a Flood, yet as ſoon as the Spirit of the Lord did lift up the Standard againſt him, from that day forward the Waters of their Deluge did decreaſe.</p>
            <p>And for our part, our Forces ſent into that Kingdom, in purſuance of that Covenant, have been ſo mercifully and manifeſtly aſſiſted, and bleſſed from Heaven (though in the mids of many dangers and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, and much want and hardſhip) and have been ſo far inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to the foyling and ſcattering of two principall Armies; Firſt, the Marqueſſe of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> his Army, And afterward, Prince <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perts</hi> and his together; And to the reducing of two ſtrong Cities, <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> that we have what to anſwer the Enemy that reproacheth us concerning that Buſineſſe, and that which may make iniquity it ſelf to ſtop her mouth. But, which is more unto us than all Victories, or whatſomever temporall Bleſſing, The Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and Uniformity therein between both Kingdoms (a principall end of that Covenant) is ſo far advanced, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service-Book, with the Holy-dayes, and many other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies contained in it, together with the Prelacy, the fountain of all theſe, are aboliſhed and taken away by Ordinance of Parliament; and a Directory for the Worſhip of God in all the three Kingdoms agreed upon in the Aſſemblies, and in the Parliaments of both Kingdoms, without a contrary voice in either; the Government of the Kirk by Congregationall Elderſhips, Claſſicall Presbyteries, Provinciall and Nationall Aſſemblies, is agreed upon by the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster,</hi> which is alſo voted and concluded in both Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> And what is yet remaining of the intended Uniformitie, is in a good way; So that let our Lot fall in other things as it may, <hi>the Will of the Lord be done;</hi> In this we rejoyce, and will rejoyce, that our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> is no loſer, but a Conquerour, that his Ordinances take place, that his Cauſe prevaileth, and the work of purging and building his Temple goeth forward, and not back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Neither yet are we ſo to underſtand <hi>the voice of the rod</hi> which lyeth heavy upon us, as if the Lords meaning were to pluck up what he hath planted, and to pull down what he hath builded in this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113099:4"/>Kingdom, to have no more pleaſure in us, to <hi>remove our Candleſtick, and to take his Kingdom from us:</hi> nay, before that our God caſt us off, and the <hi>glory depart from Iſrael.</hi> let him rather conſume us by the Sword, and the Famine, and the Peſtilence, ſo that he will but keep his own great Name from reproach and blaſphemy, and own us as his people in Convenant with him. But <hi>now there is hope in Iſrael concerning this thing,</hi> we will beleeve <hi>that we ſhall yet ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in the Land of the living:</hi> We will not caſt a way our confidence of a bleſſed Peace, &amp; of the removing of the ſcourge and caſting it in the Fire, when the Lord hath by it performed <hi>his whole Work upon mount Sion and Jeruſalem,</hi> much more will we be confident of the continuance of the bleſſings of the Goſpel, <hi>that glory may dwell in our Land. This is the day of Jacobs trouble, but he ſhall be ſaved out of it:</hi> And the time is coming, when a new Song ſhall be put in our mouths, and we ſhall ſay, <hi>This is our God, we have waited for him, and he hath ſaved us.</hi> Though the Lord ſmite us, it is the hand of a Father, not of an Enemy, he is not conſuming us, but refining us, that we may come forth as Gold out of the Fire. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide, yet not diſtreſſed; we are perplexed, but not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire; perſecuted, but not forſaken; caſt down, but not deſtroyed.</hi> We know aſſuredly there is more mercy in emptying us from Veſſell to Veſſell, than in ſuffering us to ſettle on our Lees, whereby our taſte ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in us, and our ſent not be changed.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, we come to the true langauge of this heavy judgement, and to the reall procuring cauſes thereof. <hi>For the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Jacob is all this, and for the ſins of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> God is hereby ſhewing to great and ſmall in this Land their work and their tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that they have exceeded. <hi>He openeth alſo their eare to diſcipline, and commandeth that they return from iniquity.</hi> We leave every Congregation in the Land, every Family in every Congregation, and every Perſon in every Family, to examine their own hearts and wayes, and to mourn for Congregationall, Domeſticall, and Perſonall ſins: Curſed ſhall they be who have added fuell to the fire, and now bring no water to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it; who had a great hand in the provocation, and bear no part in the humiliation.</p>
            <p>Let every one commune with his own conſcience, and repent of his, even his wickedneſſe, and ſay, <hi>What have I done?</hi> We ſhall here touch onely the Nationall ſins, or at leaſt more publike ones, than thoſe of a Family or Congregation, which we alſo intend for chief cauſes of a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike Faſt and Humiliation. If among our Nobles, Gentry, and Barons, there have been ſome ſtudying their own private intereſts more than the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113099:4"/>publike, and, <hi>Seeking their own things more than the things of Chriſt, or oppreſſing and defranding the poorer ſort and the needy, becauſe it was in the power of their hand:</hi> and if among our Miniſtry there have been divers Time-ſervers, <hi>Who have not renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, whoſe hearts have not been right before God, nor ſtedfaſt in his Covenant,</hi> who have been ſecretly haters of the <hi>Power of Godlineſſe,</hi> and of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſhall not God ſearch all this out? <hi>who will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſſe, and will make manifeſt the Councels of the hearts.</hi> In theſe alſo leaving all men to a judging and ſearching of themſelves, there are many other provocations which are apparent in all or many of this Nation, from which, <hi>though they waſh with nitre, and take much ſope,</hi> yet they cannot make themſelves clean: Becauſe of theſe <hi>the Land mourneth,</hi> and at theſe the Sword ſtriketh.</p>
            <p>As firſt, the contempt, neglect, and diſ-eſteem of the glorious Goſpel; our unbelief, unfruitfulneſſe, lukewarmneſſe, formality, and hardneſſe of heart, under all the means of Grace; our not receiving of Chriſt in our hearts, nor ſeeking to know him, and glorifie him in all his Offices. The power of Godlineſſe is hated and mocked by many to this day, and by the better ſort too much neglected, and many Chriſtian duties are not minded: as, <hi>The not ſpeaking of our own words, nor finding of our own pleaſure upon the Lords day:</hi> Holy and edifying conference both on that day, and at other occaſions: The inſtructing, admoniſhing, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and rebuking one another, as Divine Providence miniſtreth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. In many Families almoſt no knowledge nor worſhip of God to be found: yea, there are among the Miniſters who have ſtrengthened the hearts and hands of the profane more than of the godly, and have not taken <hi>heed to the Miniſtry which they have received of the Lord to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, God hath ſent the Sword to avenge the quarrell of his broken Covenant: For beſides the defection of many of this Nation under the Prelats from our firſt National Covenant, a ſin not forgotten by God, if not repented by men as well as forſaken, our latter Vows and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants have been alſo foully violated, by not contributing our uttermoſt aſſiſtance to this Cauſe, with our Eſtates and Lives; by not endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all faithfulneſſe, the diſcovery, triall, and condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Malignants, and evil Inſtruments; yea, by complying too much with thoſe, who have not onely born Arms, and given their perſonall preſence and aſſiſtance, but alſo drawn and led on others after them in the ſhedding of our Brethrens blood: Therefore is our ſin made our puniſhment, and <hi>We are filled with the fruit of our own wayes. Theſe horns
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113099:5"/>now puſh the ſides of Judah and Jeruſalem, becauſe Carpenters, when they ought and might, did not them off:</hi> And yet to this day the courſe of Juſtice is obſtructed: The Lord himſelf will execute juſtice, if men will not. But above all, let it be deeply and ſeriouſly thought of, that our Covenant is broken by the neglect of a reall Reformation of our ſelves and others under our power: let every one ask his own heart what luſt is mortified in him, or what change wrought in his life ſince, more than before the Covenant? Swearing, Curſing, Profanation of the Lords day, Fornication and other uncleanneſſe, Drunkenneſſe, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Lying, Oppreſſion, Murmuring, Repining, and other ſorts of Prophaneneſſe ſtill abound too much both in the Countrey and in our Armies: yea, there is no Reformation of ſome Members of publike Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories, which is a great diſhonour to God, and a foul ſcandall to the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we have not glorified God according to the great things which he hath done for us, nor made the right uſe of former mercies: ſince he loved us <hi>(a Nation not worthy to be beloved)</hi> he hath made us precious and honourable, but we have not walked worthy of his love: <hi>We waxed, fat and kicked, forſaking God who made us, and lightly eſteeming the Rock of our ſalvation.</hi> And this great unthankfulnes filled up our Cup.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Notwithſtanding of ſo much guiltineſſe, we did ſent forth our Armies, and undertake great ſervices preſumptuouſly, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and making our peace with God, like the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who truſting the goodneſſe of their cauſe, minded no more, but <hi>Which of us ſhall go up firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is now high time, under the feeling of ſo great a burden both of ſin and wrath, to humble our uncircumciſed hearts, <hi>to put our mouths in the duſt, if ſo be there may be hope, to wallow our ſelves in aſhes, to clothe our ſelves with our ſhame as with a garment,</hi> to juſtifie Gods righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to acknowledge our iniquity, to make our ſupplication to our Judge, and to <hi>ſeek his face,</hi> that he may <hi>pardon our ſin, and heal our Land.</hi> The Lord roareth, and ſhall not his children tremble? The God of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thundereth, and <hi>the Higheſt uttereth his voice, hailſtones and coales of fire,</hi> who will not fall down and fear before him? The fire waxeth hot, and burneth round about us, and ſhall any ſit ſtill and be ſecure? The ſtorm bloweth hard, and ſhall any ſluggard be ſtill aſleep? This is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of blaſphemy, who will not take up a lamentation? Let the Watch-men rouze up themſelves and others, and ſtrive to get their own, and their peoples hearts deeply affected, and even melted before the Lord: Let every one turn from his evil way, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113099:5"/>cry mightily to God, and give him no reſt till he repent of the evill, and ſmell a favour of reſt, and ſay, <hi>It is enough.</hi> He hath not ſaid to the ſeed of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain. <hi>We do not mourn as they that have no hope, but we will bear the indignation of the Lord, becauſe we have ſinned againſt him, untill he plead our cauſe, and execute judgement for us.</hi> And what though our Candles be put out? ſo that our Sun ſhine: What though our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be laid in the duſt? ſo that God work out his own honour, yea, our happineſſe out of our ſhame. In vain have we truſted to the arm of Fleſh: in the Lord our God is the <hi>ſalvation of Iſrael.</hi> No fleſh muſt glory before him, <hi>but he that glorieth, muſt glory in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe duties of Humiliation, Repentance, Faith, Amendment of life, and Fervent Prayer, though the principall, yet are not all which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at the hands of this Nation, but men of all ſorts and degrees, muſt timely apply themſelves to ſuch other Reſolutions and Actions as are moſt ſuteable and neceſſary at this time: Which that all may the better underſtand, and be excited and encouraged to act accordingly, let it be well obſerved, that the preſent ſtate of the Controverſie and Cauſe is no other but what hath been formerly profeſſed before God and the World, that is, The Reformation and Preſervation of Religion, The Defence of the Honour and Happineſſe of the King, and of the authority of the Parliament, together with The maintenance of our Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Lives, and Eſtates. We are not changed from our former princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and intentions, but theſe who did fall off from us to the contrary party, have now made it manifeſt, that theſe were not their ends when they ſeemed to joyn with us: <hi>Therefore are they gone out from us, becauſe they were not of us.</hi> And as our Cauſe is the ſame, ſo the danger thereof is not leſſe, but greater than before, and that from two ſorts of Enemies: Firſt, from open Enemies, we mean thoſe of the Popiſh, Prelaticall, and Malignant Faction, who have diſplayed a Banner againſt the Lord, and againſt his <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in all the three Kingdoms, being <hi>ſet on fire of Hell,</hi> and by the ſpeciall inſpiration of Satan, who is full of fury, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knows he hath but a ſhort time to reign. The Cockatrice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hatched, is now broken forth into a Viper. The danger was before feared, now it is felt; before imminent, now incumbent; before our diviſion, now our deſtruction is endeavoured; before the Sword was fourbiſhed and made ready, now the <hi>Sword is made fat with Fleſh, and drunk with Bloud,</hi> and yet it hungreth and thirſteth for more. The Queen is moſt active abroad, uſing all means for ſtrengthening the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and ſuppreſſing the Proteſtant party; inſomuch that Malignants have inſolently expreſſed their confidence, that her journey to <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113099:6"/>ſhall prove a ſucceſſefull Councell, and that this Mand, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Kingdom, ſhall have a greater power to grapple with, before the next Summer, than any which yet we have encountred with. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels have offered to the King to ſend over a greater number into both the Kingdoms: The hoſtile intentions of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> if God be not pleaſed ſtill to divert and diſable him, do plainly enough appear from his own Letters, ſent not long ſince to the Eſtates of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. In the mean time, the helliſh crue under the conduct of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate and aforefaulted <hi>Earle of Montroſe,</hi> and of <hi>Alaſter Mac-Donald,</hi> a Papiſt and an Outlaw, doth exerciſe ſuch barbarous, unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, horrid, and unheard-of cruelty, as is above expreſſion: And (if not repreſſed) what better uſage can others not yet touched expect from them, being now hardened and animated by the ſucceſſe which God hath for our humiliation and correction, permitted unto them? and if they ſhall now get leave to ſecure the High-Lands for themſelves, they will not only from thence infeſt the reſt of this Countrey, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a diverſion of our Forces in <hi>England,</hi> from the proſecution of the ends expreſſed in the Covenant of the three Kingdoms, toward which ends, as their ſervice hath been already advantageous, ſo their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is moſt neceſſary.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of Enemies, from which our preſent dangers ariſe, are ſecret Malignants and Diſ-covenanters, who may be known by theſe and the like Characters: Their ſlighting or cenſulting of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike Reſolutions of this Kirk and State: Their conſulting and labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to raiſe Jealouſies and Diviſions, to retard or hinder the execution of what is ordered by the publike Judicatories. Their ſtandering of the Covenant of the three Kingdoms and Expedition into <hi>England,</hi> as not neceſſary for the good of Religion, or ſafety of this Kingdom, or as tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the diminution of the Kings juſt power and greatneſſe: Their confounding of the Kings Honour and Authority, with the abuſe and pretence thereof, and with Commiſſions, Warrants, and Letters, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from the King, by the Enemies of this Cauſe and Covenant, as if we could not oppoſe the latter, without encroacing upon the former: Their whetting of their tongues, to cenſure and ſlander thoſe whom God hath honoured as his chief Inſtruments in this Work: Their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, juſtifying, or excuſing the proceedings of <hi>James Grahame,</hi> ſometime <hi>Earle of Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roſe,</hi> and his Complices: Their converſing or intercommuning by word or writ, with him, or other excommunicate Lords, contrary to the nature of that Ordinance of Chriſt, and to the old Acts of Generall Aſſemblies: Their making merry, and their inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113099:6"/>carriage, and the News of any proſperous ſucceſſe of the Popiſh and Malignant Armies in any of theſe Kingdoms: Their drawing of Parties and Factions, to the weakning of the common Union: Their ſpreading of Informations, That Uniformity in Religion, and the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Government, is not intended by the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> Their Endeavours, Informations, and Sollicitations, tending to weaken the hearts and hands of others, and to make them withhold their aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from this Work.</p>
            <p>Let this ſort of boſome Enemies, and diſaffected Perſons, be well marked, timely diſcovered, and carefully avoided, leſt they infuſe the poyſon of their ſeducing Councels into the minds of others: Wherein let Miniſters be faithfull, and Presbyteries vigilant and unpartiall, as they will anſwer the contrary to God, and to the Generall Aſſembly, or their Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>The cauſe and the dangers thereof being thus evidenced, unleſſe men will blot out of their hearts the love of Religion, and the Cauſe of God, and caſt off all care of their Countrey, Laws, Liberties, and Eſtates, yea, all naturall affection to the preſervation of themſelves, their Wives, Children, and Friends, and whatſoever is deareſt to them under the Sun (all theſe being in the viſible danger of a preſent ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) they muſt now or never appear actively, each one ſtretching himſelf to, yea beyond his power. It is no time to dally, nor go about the buſineſſe by halfes, nor by <hi>almost,</hi> but <hi>altogether</hi> zealous: <hi>Curſed be he that doth the Work of the Lord negligently, or dealeth falſly in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God.</hi> If we have been ſo forward to aſſiſt our Neighbour Kingdoms, ſhall we neglect to defend our own? Or ſhall the Enemies of God be more active againſt his Cauſe, than his People for it? God forbid. If the Work, being ſo far carried on, ſhall now miſcarry, and fail in our hands, our own conſciences ſhall condemne us, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity ſhall curſe us: But if we ſtand ſtoutly and ſtedfaſtly to it, the <hi>pleaſure of the Lord ſhall prosper in our hands, and all Generations ſhall call us bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let Miniſters ſtir up others by free and faithfull preaching, and by admoniſhing every one of his duty, as there ſhall be occaſion: And if it ſhall be the lot of any of them to fall under the power of the Enemy, let them through the ſtrength of Chriſt, perſevere in their integrity, chooſing affliction rather than ſin, glorifying God, and not fearing what Fleſh can do unto them.</p>
            <p>Let our Armies beware of ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, living godly, ſoberly, and righteouſly, avoiding all ſcandalous carriage, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113099:7"/>may give occaſion to others to think the worſe of their Cauſe and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and remembring that the eyes of God, Angels, and Men are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: Finally, renouncing all confidence in their own ſtrength, skill, valour, and number, and truſting onely to the <hi>God of the Armies of Iſrael,</hi> who hath fought, and will fight for them.</p>
            <p>Lat all ſorts both of high and low degree in this Kingdom, call to mind their Solemne Covenants, and pay their vows to the moſt High; and namely, that Article of our firſt Covenant, which obligeth us not to ſtay nor hinder any ſuch Reſolution, as by common conſent ſhall be found to conduce for the ends of the Covenant, but by all lawfull means to further and promove the ſame; Which lyeth as a bond upon peoples conſciences, readily to obey ſuch orders, and willingly to undergo ſuch burdens, as by the publike and common reſolution of the Eſtates of Parliament, are found neceſſary for the proſecution of the War; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Enemy cannot be ſuppreſſed without a competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Forces, and Forces cannot be kept together without mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and maintenance cannot be had without ſuch publike Burdens; which however for the preſent, not joyous, but grievous, yet it ſhall be no grief of heart afterwards, even unto the common ſort, that they have given ſome part of their neceſſary livelihood, for aſſiſting ſo good a Work. It is far from our thoughts, that the pinching of ſome, ſhould make others ſuperfluouſly to abound: It is rather to be expected of the richer ſort, that they will ſpare and defalk, not onely the pride and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, both of apparell and diet, but alſo a part of their lawfull al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance in theſe things, to contribute the ſame as a free-will-offering, beſide what they are obliged to, by Law or upblike Order, after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of godly <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who for the ſpace of twelve yeers, while the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were a building, did not eat the bread of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, that he might eaſe by ſo much the Peoples Burthens and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <p>In our laſt Covenant, there is another Article which (without the oblivion or neglect of any of the reſt) we wiſh may be well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred at this time; namely, That we ſhall aſſiſt and defend all that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into this League and Covenant, in the maintaining and purſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves, directly or indirectly, by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Combination, Perſwaſion, or Terror, to be divided and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from this bleſſed Union and Conjunction, whether to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency or neutrality in this Cauſe: According to which Article, mens reality and integrity in the Covenant, will be manifeſt and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113099:7"/>as well by their omiſſions, as by their commiſſions; as well by their not doing good, as by their doing of evil; <hi>He that is not with us, is against us; and he that gathereth not with us, ſcattereth.</hi> Whoever he be that will not according to publike order and appointment, adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his Perſon, or ſend out theſe that are under his power, or pay the Contributions impoſed for the maintenance of the Forces, muſt be taken for an Enemy, Malignant, and Covenant-breaker, and ſo invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both into the diſpleaſure of God, and Cenſures of the Kirk, and no doubt into civill puniſhments alſo to be inflicted by the State.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall prove ſo outward and perfidious, their iniquity ſhall be upon themſelves, and they <hi>ſhall bear their puniſhment:</hi> Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and good ſucceſſe ſhall follow thoſe who with purpoſe of heart cleave unto the Lord, and whoſe hearts are upright toward his glory. When we look back upon the great things which God hath done for us, and our former deliverances out of ſeverall dangers and difficulties which appeared to us inſuperable, <hi>experience breeds hope:</hi> And when we conſider how in the midſt of all our ſorrows and preſſures, the <hi>Lord our God hath given us a naile in his holy place,</hi> and hath lightened our eyes with the deſirable and beautifull ſight of his own glory in his Temple, we take it for an argument that he hath yet <hi>thoughts of peace,</hi> and a purpoſe of mercy toward us; <hi>Though for a ſmall moment he hath forſaken us, yet with great mercies he will gather us:</hi> He hath lifted up our Enemies, that their fall may be the greater, and that he may caſt them down into deſolation for ever. <hi>Ariſe, and let us be doing; The Lord of Hoſts is with us, the God of Jacob is our Refuge.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113099:8"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY. The humble Remonſtrance of the Generall Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> met at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the <hi>13</hi> day of <hi>February, 1645.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS our Record is on high, and our conſciences within us bear us witneſſe; ſo the many former Supplications and Remonſtrances to your Majeſty, from this Kirk and Kingdom, our ſolemne Covenants, and the whole courſe of our proceedings from time to time in the proſecution of this Cauſe, Do make known to the World, and we truſt alſo to your own conſcience, our loyalty and faithfull ſubjection, and how far our intentions are from the diminution of your Majeſties juſt Power and Greatneſſe; And although the ſucceſſe of many of our humble addreſſes to your Majeſty, hath been ſuch as did fruſtrate our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and hopes, yet this hath not blotted out of our hearts our loyalty, ſo often profeſſed before God and the World; but it is ſtill our Souls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and our Prayer to God for you, that your Self and your Poſterity may proſperouſly reign over this your ancient and native Kingdom, and over your other Dominions. And now as we have publiſhed a ſolemne and free Warning to the Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Burrows, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Commons of this Kingdom, concerning the preſent affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this Nation, and their ſins procuring the ſame; So when we call to mind, that God accepteth not the perſons of men, and that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt are not to be winked at in their ſins; We aſſure our ſelves, that the beſt and moſt reall teſtimony which we can give at this preſent, of the tenderneſſe and uprightneſſe of our affection to your Majeſties true Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, is this our humble and faithfull Repreſentation of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties great and growing dangers, and the cauſes thereof; Of which, if we ſhould be ſilent, our conſciences would condemne us, and <hi>the ſtones themſelves would immediately cry out.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113099:8"/>
            <p>The troubles of our hearts are enlarged, and our fears increaſed in your Majeſties behalf, perceiving that your Peoples patience is above meaſure tempted, and is like Cart preſt down with ſheaves, and ready to break, while as beſide many former deſignes and endeavours to bring deſolation and deſtruction upon us, (which were (and we truſt all of that kinde ſhall be) by the marvellous and mercifull providence of God diſcovered and diſappointed) Our Countrey is now infeſted, the blood of divers of our Brethren ſpilt, and other acts of moſt barbarous and horrid cruelty exerciſed, by the curſed crew of the Iriſh Rebels and their Complices in this Kingdom, under the conduct of ſuch as have Commiſſion and Warrant from your Majeſty. And unleſſe we prove unfaithfull both to God and to your Majeſty, we cannot conceale ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther danger which is infinitely greater than that of your Peoples diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Therefore we the Servants of the moſt high God, and your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt loyall Subjects, in the humility and grief of our hearts, fall down before your Throne, and in the Name of our Lord and Maſter <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who ſhall judge the world in righteouſneſſe, both great and ſmall, and in the Name of this whole Nationall Kirk, which we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, We make bold to warn your Majeſty freely, that the guilt which cleaveth faſt to your Majeſty and to your Throne, is ſuch, as (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever flattering preachers, or unfaithfull councellors may ſay to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) if not timely repented, cannot but involve your Self and your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity under the wrath of the ever-living God, For your being guilty of the ſhedding of the blood of many thouſands of your Majeſties beſt Subjects; For your permitting the Maſſe, and other Idolatry, both in your own Family, and in your own Dominions; For your authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, by the Book of Sports, the profanation of the Lords Day; For your not puniſhing of publike ſcandals, and much profaneneſſe, in, and about your Court; For the ſhutting of your eares from the humble and juſt deſires of your faithfull Subjects; For your complying too much with the Popiſh party many wayes, and namely, by concluding the Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Arms in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and your embracing the councels of thoſe who have not ſet God nor good before their eyes; For your reſiſting and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing this Cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, your own honour and happineſſe, and the peace and ſafety of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; and for what other cauſes your Majeſty is moſt conſcious, and may beſt judge and ſearch your own conſcience (nor would we have mentioned any particulars, if they had not been publike and known.) For all which it is high time for your Majeſty to fall down at the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool of the King of Glory, to acknowledge your offence, to repent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113099:9"/>timely, to make your peace with God through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (whoſe blood is able to waſh away your great ſin) and to be no longer as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that the Son of God reign over you and your Kingdoms in his pure Ordinances of Church-government and Worſhip. Theſe things if your Majeſty do, it ſhall be no grief of heart unto you afterward, a bleſſing is reſerved for you, and you ſhall find favour with God, and with your People, and with all the Churches of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> But if your Majeſty refuſe to hearken to this wholſome councell (which the Lord forbid) we have diſcharged our own conſciences, we take God and Men to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, That we are blameleſſe of the ſad Conſequences which may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and we ſhall wait upon the Lord, who, <hi>when he maketh inquiſition for blood, will not forget the cry of the humble.</hi> In the mean while, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching your Majeſty to take notice That we are not ſtaggering or fainting through diffidence of the ſucceſſe of this Cauſe and Covenant of the three Kingdoms, unto which, as God hath already given manifold Teſtimonies of his favour and bleſſing; ſo it is our ſtedfaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken confidence, that this is the Work and Cauſe of God, which ſhall gloriouſly prevaile againſt all oppoſition, and from which; with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the grace of God, we ſhall never ſuffer our ſelves to be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or withdrawn, but ſhall zealouſly and conſtantly in our ſeverall Vocations, endeavour with our Eſtates and Lives, the purſuing and promoving thereof.</p>
            <p>That which we have concluded concerning Uniformity in Religion between both Kingdoms, is to be humbly offered to your Majeſty from the Commiſſioners of this Kingdom, for your Royall Conſent and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. Although your Majeſty was not pleaſed to vouchſafe us the preſence of your Commiſſioner, according to the ſupplications of the Commiſſioners of the preceding Generall Aſſembly, yet we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded with as much reſpect to your Majeſties honour, and as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our duty, as if your Royall Perſon had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the mids of us: And we ſhall ſtill continue our Prayers for you, that God would graciouſly incline your heart to the Councels of Truth and Peace, and grant unto your Majeſty a long and happy Raign, that we may live under you a peaceable and quiet life, in all Godlineſſe and Honeſty.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
